Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  - Theodore Imbasciani oral history interview conducted by Ashlee McGlone, July 30, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 244
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Terrence Legrady oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, July 31, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 245
    Terrence Legrady is currently a Suffolk County Police officer at Shelter Island. On 9/11/01, he was a rookie NYPD at the 102nd Precinct in Queens. He had only been on the force for 1.5 years. He was engaged at that time and his fiancé was a school teacher. His father is also retired NYPD, and has two cousins that are FDNY. The morning of the attacks, Terrence was driving home on the LIE because he worked the night shift. When he got home, his commander called him back in. Being a rookie, he did not really know what to expect, but due to the magnitude of this tragedy, there is no way that anyone could know. He drove back to Manhattan via the LIE HOV lane. There were checkpoints along the way, and then they drove over lawns to get to the precinct. It was strange to Terrence to see everyone in the locker rooms and in the building at one time because he was used to seeing only his platoon. The atmosphere was slightly chaotic, but he was glad to see so many retired cops volunteering, even if it was just to answer the phone. They were assigned their orders according to “levels of mobilization.” His first assignment was security in front of a synagogue in Queens. The community and rabbis were grateful for his presence. He stayed there until the threat was gone. On 9/12/11, their shifts were changed to 16hr (instead of 12hr). He stayed on for his night shift and was assigned to Ground Zero. NYPD buses would transport him from the 107th Precinct. Terrence had worked for two days before he finally was able to go home and see his fiancé and get some sleep. Terrence will never forget and has never experienced anything like it since, the tremendous sense of unity. He and his fellow officers worked in very rough neighborhoods. He was used to being hated and spit on and had dirty diapers thrown at him, but people would come up to him and offer to buy him coffee, people lined up along the FDR Drive clapping and cheering for them. Even the computer surveillance cameras in the patrol cars were quiet because the community had all come together in this time of crisis. Terrence was assigned to “the Pit”. He stated that he has a terrible memory, but everything related to 9/11 has been “etched into his brain”. His first vivid memory was of Trinity Church with all the Missing Person’s flyers. They were allowed to take meal breaks, but mostly everyone forfeited them and helped search for survivors. The enormity of the pit was indescribable. When they blew the horn, everyone had to stop what they were doing, engines turned off, and everything was silenced. They would wait to hear for signs of life. If the horn blew twice, you had to run because another building or structure was going down. Terrence had seen a man climbing a telephone pole so he approached him to assess the situation. The man was from the EPA who was testing the air. The EPA told him that the air was fine, so everyone removed their masks. Terrence saw thousands of rescue workers and no one was wearing masks. Since he worked nights, he was unable to really see how bad it was. After several days, there was a distinct decaying body smell mixed with burnt rubber and metal. Terrence commended the efforts of the Red Cross volunteers. The Red Cross had made a nearby school into a hotel for the rescue workers to rest and eats. They gave him a clean cot with bedding and a mint on the pillow, along with a care package of toiletries; they even provided them with wake up calls. Terrence worked side by side with someone who is just a year younger than him who now has a rare stomach cancer that is attributed to his exposure at 9/11. Terrence is now getting yearly monitoring even though he does not have any major symptoms. He commended the WTC Health and Monitoring Program with having great workers and feels it’s a great program for the First Responders. In 2005, Terrence left NYPD and went to “the County”. His last post as a NYPD officer was at a teacher’s protest on Church and Vesey. It was the first time he had been back since 9/11. It was an odd experience to see everything cleaned up, rebuilt and functioning anew. It was very symbolic for him as he exited and moved on to a better job. Terrence has certain visual, audio and scent “triggers” that bring back vivid memories of 9/11. He does discuss 9/11 with other officers when they are socializing. At each anniversary, he does what he can to commemorate that time in history. He honors those who ran into the burning, collapsing buildings as heroes.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Ernest Eifert oral history interview conducted by Amanda Mancuso, August 4, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 246
    Ernest grew up in the Bronx and started working for his brother-in-law’s contracting company at the age of 13. From there he started working in construction for NYC at various places, including the New York Public Library, the Museum of Natural History, the NYC transit authority, and the NYC housing authority. On the day of 9/11 Ernest was working for the housing authority in an apartment close to the World Trade Center buildings. A woman in the apartment building told Ernest and his coworkers what had just happened and they rushed to another building they had worked in the past to get a better view of the towers from the building roof. At that time the only form of communication that was still working were their walkie-talkies, where they were hearing a lot of misinformation about other attacks at places like the Mall of America and Washington, D.C. The day after the attacks Ernest went to work, where they received a phone call from the emergency services of NYC saying they needed five carpenters to come to ground zero to build ramps on site, so that the debris trucks would not crush the fire hoses. Ernest and a few of his coworkers first went to buy disposable cameras so that they could document what they were going to see, and then headed to the site, which he described as a “landscape of a nightmare”. Ernest worked at ground zero for two days; while there he could not help but notice how organized it was, and how so many people came together to help. The most memorable moment for him was when he walked past a line of firefighters and caught eyes with each one of them and saw the horrible looks on their faces. After a 14 hour work day, Ernest went home and did not want to go back to the site to work again. Two weeks later he returned to the site with his 9 year old son to see the progress because he thought it was important for his son to see what was going on. Another notable memory of his was that he noticed the FBI agents were wearing gas masks and Tyvec suits, while the responders and other workers were wearing only paper masks. He believed the FBI probably knew something that they didn’t about the hazardous environment. The number of people he knows who have been diagnosed with a health issue after working at ground zero has doubled in recent years. Since 9/11, Ernest is still reminded of the attacks when he sees pieces of the building displayed as memorials, and when he hears fighter jets flying low over Yankee Stadium during opening day. He states “everything has changed”.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Donato (Danny) oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, August 5, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 247
    Danny was born and raised in Queens, NY, but now lives with his family in Long Island, NY. His parents emigrated to NY from Italy in their early 20s, and had five sons—who all became NYPD officers and 9/11 responders. Danny is the youngest. He was in the NYPD for twenty years; he retired a couple of years ago. Danny credits his lifelong love of soccer with helping to instill values that no group of people is all bad or all good, but that each person must be judged on their own merit. Soccer allowed him to meet and befriend people of all different creeds and races, and he says he even picked up foreign languages on the field. He continued playing throughout adulthood, finding that his knowledge of the game helped him in investigations when trying to build trust with potential informants. After 9/11, the NYPD soccer team he played with collected donations and went on humanitarian trips to places like South America and Korea. An undercover detective in the narcotics division, Danny was asked to join the NYPD intelligence division when it was formed in March 2001. He remarks that it essentially changed over to an anti-terrorism unit after 9/11 occurred, and that the NYPD overall was forever changed. On the morning of 9/11, Danny dropped his infant son off with his caretaker in Queens, where he was still living, and decided to drive his wife to her office in midtown Manhattan, which he didn’t normally do because it made him late to work. As he drove south, he noticed a police car racing by and assumed there had been an incident at the Empire State Building. When the squad car continued downtown, Danny realized his mistake and also noticed the crowd waiting for the bus all looking south instead of (as would be typical) looking in the direction from which the bus would approach. He turned on 1010 WINS and heard the report that planes had crashed into the Towers. When Danny got to his office, only one sergeant was there. They drove to City Hall Park together and found about ten other officers from their precinct. There was chaos around them, and while they waited for word on what to do, they helped bleeding, dust-covered people to ambulances. While they were stationed at the park, the first tower fell, which they couldn’t see because they were too close. The ground vibrated as if there were an earthquake or the street was caving in, and they ran, helping others along the way. He remarks upon the irony of going from running toward the buildings to running away from them and recalls feeling very numb and thinking that the situation was surreal, a word he usually hates. The group of cops felt great frustration at having to stand around when they could have been helping, especially because some of them were trained EMTs. While they were waiting, he walked to Chambers Street to see if he could find a phone. At this point, he says, he seemed to understand that this was a terrorist attack, and he felt incredible urgency to get in touch with his wife and tell her to leave Manhattan as soon as possible, not knowing if more attacks were to come. Despite feelings of helplessness and numbness, Danny felt like he had to act. Although they were told not to go to the Pile, he and another officer joined the bucket brigade in their dress clothes, working for hours. He says that it felt useful in the moment but in retrospect he wonders how much of a difference it made. He says, “It’s like being a lifeguard and there are all these people drowning—who do you help first?” He remembers the endless lines of responders—EMTs, firemen, cops, and civilians. At one point, a man came up to him and fed him a slice of pizza, which is one of the most arresting memories he has of that day. After a few hours on the brigade, they rejoined their squad. The intelligence division made temporary offices in the Intrepid, while the FBI camped out in an adjacent parking structure. Danny’s division was responsible for following up and investigating anything that came through the tip lines, and he recalls how frustrating it was to investigate fruitlessly. They went to the site daily to perform grid searches, looking for any evidence or relevant clues in the rubble. One some days, they had painter’s masks, but often wore no protective covering—only on the day the FBI joined them were they given Tyvek suits. He has little memory of going home or being with his family during this time. After a couple of years of doing this work, he was asked to join a task force to investigate/infiltrate mosques in Harlem, during which time he ran Hamas investigations for 5-6 years and even learned some Arabic. Danny retired spontaneously one day, going to One Police Plaza to file his paperwork, where he met Commissioner Kelly. Although he misses the work, which was a huge part of his identity, he does not miss the frustrations and feeling at times like he cared more than the department did. Despite all being responders, he and his brothers didn’t discuss 9/11 for many years, even when they started becoming ill. He knows now that two brothers have cancer, and he also has health issues and suffers from insomnia. Certain things—like news of what is happening in Gaza—trigger memories for him. He says 9/11 totally reshaped who he is; he has more negative feelings toward the government and feels that in these situations it’s always the regular people who suffer. Danny’s interview had very present themes of equality and cooperation. He insists that he is not a hero, and was raised not to take glory, but simply do his part, which is what he wants his kids and the next generation to do as well.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Elias Jimenez oral history interview conducted by Amanda Mancuso, August 5, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 248
    Elias Jimenez is an Environmental Engineer for the MTA, and worked on 2 Broadway on 9/11/2001. He is a Vietnam Veteran and served as a combat medic. He is a husband, father of two daughters and grandfather. He was raised in CT but graduated in Puerto Rico. He earned his degree at Queens College. He began his career in pharmaceutical sales and then crossed over to engineering. On the morning of the attacks, “Eli” worked on the second floor of his office building across from Liberty Park and the Wall Street Bull. He had heard a faint rumble and then saw paper falling all around when he looked out the window. It looked like confetti, but it wasn’t because the papers were full sheets. He heard that a plane had struck one of the towers, so since he had emergency training, he went outside to see if he could help. He walked to the corner of Vesey and Greenwich and saw a crowd of people. He saw building in flames but the damaged seemed to be contained and there was no real panic. While Eli was standing there, he heard engines overhead, he looked up and saw the under carriage of the second plane. He heard the engines rev just before impact. His thoughts were with the passengers, he had hoped that they weren’t frightened; he knew that they didn’t suffer. It was obvious to him that this was a terrorist attack. He knelt down, cried and was in shock. Silica and debris was falling all around from the disintegrated building and plane. Then Eli felt the earth quake, and then he saw a swarm of people trying to out run a tsunami of greyish white debris. He was blinded by the dust and silica. He was being bombarded by running people as he tried to stand his ground. He had seen many horrific things in Vietnam, but none compared to this destruction of so many innocent lives. It was evident to him that there were no survivors. Eli walked over the Brooklyn Bridge to where his brother-in-law lived. It was a mass exodus over the bridges. He cannot forget the sight of looking over the bridge and seeing the remains of the buildings. It had been reduced to fire and smoke. It took him 3-4 hours to get to his brother-in-law’s house. He doesn’t remember how he got home to LI, but when he did, his wife was crying. Eli reported to work the next day, but his building on Broadway was closed. His office relocated on Livingston St, but he convinced his boss that he wouldn’t be productive there, and he would best be served in a triage center. He proved first aid to the workers with callouses and bruises. He worked five days straight for 8-10 hours each day. Then he continued to work the weekends for 6 months after. The Saturday following the attacks, it rained. Eli found a picture of a flag floating down a stream of water down the subway track at the Fulton St station. I was a replica of the US flag with children’s sentiments and signatures all over it. They made it to honor the First Responders. Eli didn’t use his respirator all the time, and the face masks were not helpful and it was difficult to communicate with them on. He saw EPA workers use cassettes to measure the asbestos, but he knew they were ineffective because they would become overloaded due to the amount of silica in the air. Thirteen years later, Eli continues to be affected by the tragedy. He has difficulty sleeping, and has no tolerance for nonsense and stupid things. He still works downtown and sees how everyone’s lives went back to normal as if nothing had happened. He is grateful to have had the opportunity to volunteer.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Alan Z. Fromm oral history interview conducted by Ashlee McGlone, August 6, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 249
    Alan grew up in Brooklyn, New York. He has been married for thirty-five years and has two kids. Alan currently lives in Plainview, New York. He attended Brooklyn College for his undergraduate and graduate degrees. At first, Alan was a Pre-med major but later switched to television and radio production. Alan worked at Corporate TV and ABC TV for seven years. The majority of Alan’s career was with Credit Swiss First Boston where he served as a Vice President for training. He currently works for a pharmaceutical company that produces generic pharmaceuticals in Hauppauge, New York. During 9/11, Alan was working in building 5 at the World Trade Center. His job at the time was a director of training for Credit Swiss First Boston. Alan’s job function was to move people around from office to office. He started the day in the company’s Madison Avenue office. Alan went there that morning and noticed that everything was perfectly in place. He felt relieved because he usually had to fix the layout of the office. After Alan viewed the office at Madison Avenue, he took the M-train to the main office which was at the World Trade. However, on his way to the office the M-train had stopped at Cortland Street for a very long time. Alan had to be re-directed to Rector Street. The reason for the re-direction was due to a smoke condition. At first, Alan didn’t think too much about being re-directed because it did happen before. On the other hand, once Alan got off the train at Rector Street he saw people running, papers blowing everywhere and saw smoke in the air. Alan noticed a bunch of firemen standing around and approached them in order to find out answers. The firemen believed that a small plane had crashed into the tower. However, as Alan was standing around he and the firemen had heard the second plane’s engine rumbling. Alan saw the second plane go right into the tower. When Alan saw the second plane hit he asked the firemen to help him search for anyone who was at the building where he had worked. Alan was a Fire Warden and believed it was his duty to help rescue people from building five. He and the firefighters started walking towards Alan’s office. As Alan was walking he noticed the destruction, the debris and the amount of body parts that consumed the area around the World Trade. Alan witnessed the debris and people falling from the towers. He went into building five and saw a jet engine in the cafeteria of the building. Alan searched all nine floors of the building to find anyone who was in distress. Alan left the building and noticed that people were going into nearby stores to consume necessities that were needed to help the wounded. He and a bunch of firemen opened up a cooler at one of the street kiosks located near the sight. Alan helped handout juice and soda. He noticed that people were covered in jet fuel. Alan was about to leave until one of the towers came down. There was a loud rumble and huge gust of wind from the collapsing tower. Alan hid underneath an ambulance. No one believed that the towers were going to fall down. There was a huge dust cloud that consumed the area around the World Trade. Alan got knocked out by the falling debris and later woke up inside of the same ambulance that he was hiding underneath. Alan had a hard time breathing and was covered head to toe in a thick layer of dust and dirt. Alan described the World Trade site as a warzone. Everything was in black and white due to the dust and the towers falling. Alan left the chaotic scene and was trying to make his way back to the Madison Avenue office. On his way to the office, Alan sat down on a curb and broke down crying. A woman approached Alan and invited him into her apartment in order for him to clean up. When he got to the woman’s apartment the phone lines were down and the television was on showing the event that had just occurred at the World Trade. Alan left the woman’s apartment and made it to the Madison office where he was greeted by his fellow workers and was sent to the medical center in the building. Here, Alan received new clothes and started making plans to go home. Alan doesn’t remember how he made it back home. However, Alan distinctively remembers that people were eating meals at cafes and enjoying life while the towers were collapsing. Later that night, Alan’s community got together and said prayers for the victims. Alan had to start back at work right away because it was his job to make sure people had a place for them to work. The railroads were up and running. Alan was shocked about the amount of people who had returned to work the next day. However, some workers never showed up at their jobs ever again and Alan noticed that everyone had this looming atmosphere over their heads while they were working. When Alan returned home to his family his daughter had trouble coping with the 9/11 events. Alan’s daughter realized that she almost lost her father which resulted in her having difficulties sleeping. Alan went back to the site a couple of weeks later and the site still had a stench in the air. The events of 9/11 has made Alan become more aware of his surroundings. He keeps a watchful eye-out for anything that may seem suspicious. In addition, Alan mentioned that there was a huge shift in the mentality of New Yorkers after 9/11. People became more forgiving of one another after the event.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Timothy oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, August 7, 2014, AFC 2015/048: 250